Guide to the William David Sherman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William David Sherman papers
1958-2007
YCAL MSS 224
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.81
(13 boxes)
The William David Sherman papers contain correspondence, writings, and other materials documenting the personal and professional activities of American author William David Sherman. Correspondence in the collection consists chiefly of incoming letters from English-language authors and literary scholars active during the mid to late twentieth century, including Asa Benveniste, Basil Bunting, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Rachel Blau DuPlessis, David Goodis, Bill Griffiths, Jeremy Hilton, Lyn Lifshin, Susan Smith Nash, Frances Presley, and Tom Raworth. The largest correspondence files are from Corman and Griffiths, poet and curator of the Eric Mottram Archive at King's College, London. Griffiths's letters, for example, discuss literary matters, the literary scene in England, and life in northeastern England. Writings consist chiefly of drafts of poetry collections, but there are also novels, short stories, copies of Sherman's graduate student work at SUNY Buffalo, and offprints for articles by other writers. Other materials include audio and video recordings, computer disks, subject files, photographs, and printed materials.
Sherman, William David
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. and Stanton Francis Kennedy funds, 2005 and 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 3 and 13 (computer disks): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 7-9 (audiovisual material): Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
William David Sherman (1940-)
William David Sherman, American author, educator, and publisher, was born December 24, 1940, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Louis and Gertrude (Benn) Sherman. Sherman was educated at Temple University (B.A., 1962) and SUNY Buffalo (M.A., 1964, Ph.D., 1968), after which he taught as an instructor and lecturer at various institutions in the U.S and Great Britain over most of the next two decades before settling in French Polynesia.
Biographical information taken from "William David Sherman." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2001. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 8 June 2012.
Scope and Contents
The William David Sherman papers contain correspondence, writings, and other materials documenting the personal and professional activities of American author William David Sherman. Correspondence in the collection consists chiefly of incoming letters from English-language authors and literary scholars active during the mid to late twentieth century, including Asa Benveniste, Basil Bunting, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Rachel Blau DuPlessis, David Goodis, Bill Griffiths, Jeremy Hilton, Lyn Lifshin, Susan Smith Nash, Frances Presley, and Tom Raworth. The largest correspondence files are from Corman and Griffiths, poet and curator of the Eric Mottram Archive at King's College, London. Griffiths's letters, for example, discuss literary matters, the literary scene in England, and life in northeastern England. Writings consist chiefly of drafts of poetry collections, but there are also novels, short stories, copies of Sherman's graduate student work at SUNY Buffalo, and offprints for articles by other writers. Other materials include audio recordings, computer disks, subject files, photographs, and printed materials.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: 2005 Acquisition and December 2007 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; England, North East; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Authors; Benveniste, Asa; Bunting, Basil, 1900-; Corman, Cid, 1924-; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005; DuPlessis, Rachel Blau; Goodis, David, 1917-1967; Griffiths, Bill, 1948-2007; Hilton, Jeremy; Lifshin, Lyn, 1944-; Mottram, Eric; Nash, Susan Smith, 1958-; Presley, Frances; Raworth, Tom, 1938-; Sherman, William David; King's College London; State University of New York at Buffalo
- 2005 Acquisition, 1966-2002; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Materials.
  Scope and Contents
  The 2005 Acquisition contains correspondence, writings, and other materials. Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming letters from English-language authors and literary scholars active during the mid to late twentieth century, including Asa Benveniste, Basil Bunting, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Rachel Blau DuPlessis, David Goodis, Bill Griffiths, Jeremy Hilton, Lyn Lifshin, Susan Smith Nash, Frances Presley, and Tom Raworth. The largest correspondence files are from Cid Corman and Bill Griffiths, poet and curator of the Eric Mottram Archive at King's College, London. Griffiths's letters, for example, discuss literary matters, the literary scene in England, and life in northeastern England. The correspondence also includes letters from friends and acquaintances in Moorea, French Polynesia, where Sherman resided in the early to mid 1990s.
  The writings include corrected holograph drafts for poems, stories, and essays by Sherman, and several offprints for articles by other writers. Other materials include printed ephemera relating to Sherman and Shreela Ray.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. Fund, 2005.
  - Correspondence
    - Benveniste, Asa, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Bunting, Basil, undated (Box 1)
    - Corman, Cid, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Coupry, Caroline, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
      Includes photograph of Coupry
    - Creeley, Robert, 1994 March 30 (Box 1)
    - Cyberwit.net, 2001 July 9 (Box 1)
    - Danielsson, Bengt, 1994 July 21 (Box 1)
    - Dash, Braja Kishore, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Decottignies, Jacques; Decottgnies, Jean, 1993-1999, undated (Box 1)
    - DuPlessis, Rachel Blau, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Fiedler, Leslie, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Garwin, Richard L., 1995 (Box 1)
      Includes copy of letter from Garwin to Libération
    - Glissenti, Emma, 1999 January 25 (Box 1)
    - Goodis, David, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Griffith, William, 1994-1998, undated (Box 1)
      Includes photograph
    - Grilikhes, Alexandra, 1991-1997, undated (Box 1)
    - [Hauata, Teuruna?], 1996-2000 (Box 1)
    - Herring, Janet, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Heyerdahl, Thor, undated (Box 1)
    - Hilton, Jeremy, 1997-2000 (Box 1)
    - Hirshon, Tea, 1999, undated (Box 1)
      Includes photograph and clipping
    - Hoffman, Daniel, 1991 April 28 (Box 1)
    - Holmes, David, 1999 June 21 (Box 1)
      Includes copy of letter to Sherman from Antonio Colomar
    - International Poets Academy, 1996 [June 11?] (Box 1)
    - Lifshin, Lyn, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
      Includes copies of poems
    - Michener, James A., 1991 May 28 (Box 1)
    - Nash, Susan Smith, 1993-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Pennington, Jim, 1991-2002, undated (Box 1)
    - Presley, Frances, 1995-2000 (Box 1)
    - Raworth, Tom, 1991 June 29 (Box 2)
    - Ray, Shreela, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Skelt, Peterjon; Skelt, Yasmin, 1995 February 20 (Box 2)
    - Skoula-Peripherake, Marlena, 1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Steptoe, Lamont B., 1998-2000 (Box 2)
    - Thomas, R. S. (Ronald Stuart), 1998 (Box 2)
    - Yatlee, Lee, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - First name only, 1992-1999, undated (Box 2)
    - Third party letters, 1990 August 19 (Box 2)
      Copy of letter from Robert Creeley to John Rety
  - Writings
    - Writings of William David Sherman
      - "Against Language," poems, drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "Amazon Diary," drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "Beckhole Wicca," poem, online version, printout, 1999 June 19 (Box 2)
      - "Caroline in Moonlight," drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "David Goodis, Writer," essay, printed version, Exquisite Corpse, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - "David Goodis/Dark Passage," obituary, printed version, Sight and Sound, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - "Fernando Pessoa," poem, draft, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2)
      - "Five Poems for Frances Presley," drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "The Mana of the Moai," essays, drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "An Occupational Hazard," [short story?], drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, and typescript, undated (Box 2)
      - "A Tale for Tusitala," story, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - Untitled poems, undated (Box 2)
    - Writings of Others
      - Evans, Paul
        - "Poem improvised on the back cover..." draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - Holland, Norman Norwood
        - "Freud and H.D.," essay, printed version, International Journal of Psycho-Analysis, photocopy, 1969 (Box 2)
        - "H.D. et Freud," essay, offprint, Études Freudiennes, undated (Box 2)
      - Kaplan, Leonard V.
        - "Can Rational Instrumentalism Do All That?" essay, offprint, Windsor Yearbook of Access to Justice, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Maud, Ralph
        - "Archetypal Depth Criticism and Melville," essay, reprint, College English, 1983 November (Box 2)
      - Mitchell, Paige
        - [Poems], drafts, typescript, photocopies, 1980, undated (Box 2)
      - Molesworth, Charles
        - "We Have Come This Far," essay, reprint, Soundings, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Mottram, Eric
        - "Poe's Pym, and the American Social Imagination," essay, offprint, undated (Box 2)
      - Ott, Gil
        - "Ladder," poem, printed version, Loot, 1983 July (Box 2)
      - Ray, Shreela
        - "Night Conversations With None Other," typecript, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - Rinella, Vincent
        - "Ethical Issues and Psychiatric Cost-Containment Strategies," essay, offprint, International Journal of Law and Psychiatry, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Other Materials
    - Computer media, undated
      Conditions Governing Access
      Computer disk is restricted. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services.
      - ARCHIVE, 2005-ycal-1020-e-0001; 1 (Box 3)
        Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - CV for Sherman, undated (Box 2)
    - Material relating to Shreela Ray, 1978-1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Printed ephemera, 1991-1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Stamps from "Polynesie Française", 1995, undated (Box 2)
- December 2007 Acquisition, 1958-2007; 3.76; (10 boxes)
  Organized into three series: Writings, Audiovisual Materials, and Other Materials.
  The December 2007 Acquisition contains writings, correspondence, and other materials. Writings, arranged alphabetically by title, consist chiefly of drafts of poetry collections, but there are also novels, short stories, and copies of Sherman's graduate student work at SUNY Buffalo, including his thesis, "The Hero as Athlete" (1964), and dissertation, "The Contemporary American Novel" (1968).
  In addition to writings, there are audiovisual materials, computer disks, correspondence and subject files, photographs, and printed materials. The audiovisual materials consist chiefly of audio recordings (on reel-to-reel and cassette tapes) of interviews, readings, and events, with Sherman and others. The computer disks appear to contain drafts of writings.
  Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Stanton Francis Kennedy Fund, 2007.
  Boxes 7-9 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be available. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Writings
    - Vendor description of archive, undated (Box 4)
    - "Amazon Diary", 1977 (Box 4)
    - "Ayeshah: a Dream of Love", undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - "Branch Redd", undated (Box 4)
    - "Cat of 9 Tales", undated (Box 4)
    - "The Contemporary American Novel: Beyond Comic Anarchy", 1967 May (Box 4)
    - "Cyrene Song", undated (Box 4)
    - "The Door Has a Creaking Latch", undated (Box 4)
    - "The Encounter", undated (Box 4)
    - "Flatbush Max", undated (Box 4)
    - "Further Incidents Along the Trail", undated (Box 4)
    - "Handwritten Unpublished Poetry", 2003, undated (Box 4)
    - "The Hero as Athlete in Contemporary American Fiction: The Baseball Novels of Bernard Malamud and Mark Harris", 1964 May (Box 5)
    - "I'd give Anything For a Woman Like Margo Lane: Miscellaneous Early Poems", 1990, undated (Box 5)
    - "in his time", undated (Box 5)
    - "Lonesome Times", undated (Box 5)
    - "The Love of Scarlet Phantoms", undated (Box 5)
      20071207-12639-0013: 7
    - "Mermaids", undated (Box 5)
    - "Miscellaneous Poems", 1986 (Box 5)
      Includes photographs
    - "Not Having Sex in French Polynesia: Poems & Prose, 1996-'98", [circa 1996-1998] (Box 5)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes, undated (Box 5)
    - "Of Rapa Nui", 1997-2000, undated (Box 5)
    - "On the Joys of Spring", [1958?] (Box 5)
    - "The Pageant", 2001 (Box 5)
      Includes letters, in French, to Philippe Garnier
    - "Poems For the Hurt", undated (Box 6)
    - "Polynesian Threnody", undated (Box 6)
    - "Rapa Nui", undated (Box 6)
    - "Spanish Songs in Mandaine Land", undated (Box 6)
    - "Stand Upon the Ceiling", undated (Box 6)
    - "The Susan Poems", undated (Box 6)
    - "The Time the A's West West: Selected Poems, 1965-'74", [circa 1965-1974] (Box 6)
    - "To Caroline", 1993, undated (Box 6)
    - "Transgressive Durations", undated (Box 6)
    - "Triptych", undated (Box 6)
    - "25 Nights in England", undated (Box 6)
    - "until the earthrape stops", [circa 1974-1979] (Box 6)
  - Audiovisual Materials
    Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Maximus To Himself", 1967; YCALMSS224_0001; 1; 00:05:53 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002102301547)
      A film by Theodora Cichy and William D. Sherman (1967), based on the poem "Maximus, to himself" by Charles Olson and utilizing verses from Ewan MacColl The Shoals of Herring
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Allen Fisher, from 'place book 1'", undated; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109974825)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
    - "[Hull?] Environment", [circa 1967-1968]; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109974858)
    - "Poetry Reading, Aberystwyth", 1969; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109974841)
      A list of contents is included with this audiotape reel.
      "The Freewheelin' Bob Dylan"
      "The New Briton Gazette", volume 2
      "The Concert for Bangla Desh"
    - "The Gregynog Heavy", 1970; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109974833)
      Wah-Wah Spirituals at the Garden
      Dylan's Return
      Randy
      Paul Simon
      Simon (with Stephanie)
      Joni Mitchell
      Ralph McTell
      Christy Moore
    - [Poetry Reading], undated; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109974866)
      Contents on this audiotape reel include a reading of "Asphodel, That Greeny Flower" and music from artists such as Linda Ronstadt, Jackson Browne and Johnny Cash.
      A written note accompanies this audiotape reel. It reads: Dear B and B, The reading of "Asphodel" is none too good, but it's there if you want it. "Romanze d'Amour" is for Barbara, and "Lost at Sea" is Bill's presidential campaign song! Guess you'll prefer the second side...Love and peace, Domi
    - "Songs and Snippets", undated; 1 (Box 8, Item barcode 39002109974874)
      Songs on this audiotape reel include "All Along the Watchtower" and Knockin' on Heaven's Door"...for Bill and Barbara. Detailed notes on the songs and their meaning are included.
    - "The Teuruna Tape", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974882)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974890)
    - "'Hello, Pecos' Dominic Williams", 1987; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974908)
      Home recordings on this audiocassette are listed.
      Final Farewell
      Kiss It All Away
      Broken Hearts
      Love Believes in Me
      How Do I Love You?
      Le It Be Me
      Prime Cut Meat
      Famous Blue Raincoat
      St. James' Infirmary
      Perfect Possibilities
      Number in the Book
    - "Liesl Ermin, ship's harpess; Marilyn Johnson, ship's singer", 1987; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974916)
    - "Medley / Samoa and Moorea", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974924)
    - "Tsimchanango, free Tibet", 1991; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974940)
    - "Marianne Moore", 1975; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974957)
    - "American English", Dominic Williams, 1987; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974965)
      A list of contents is included with this audiocassette.
      Still in Love
      Tonight and Every Night
      All of Your Life Ahead
      Liberal and Enlightened
      Man of the Mountains
      Summertime
      Call It Anything But 'War'
      What's One More Song?
      City Boy in Paradise
      Jolly Jack
      The Morning After
      Two Nations
      Set Me Up Good
      Tonight and Every Night (reprise)
    - "A Hambone Sketch", 2000; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974973)
    - "Chrissie Waldron formerly of the New Bracken Band", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974981)
      Songs on this audiocassette include: The Nightvisiting Song, Highland Widows Lament, Sandgate Dandling, Liverpool Lullaby
    - "Return of 'One Take Willy'" / "Keeping It Live", 1983; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109974999)
      The audiocassette contains a list of contents. It includes songs from "Return of 'One Take Willy'" performed by 'Scratch Band'. The first three songs from "Keeping It Live" were performed at Family Folk Night, Clifton Green School, Salford by the new braken band. Dom Williams performed at The Eagle and Child, Whitefield.
    - "I Want Burning", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975004)
    - "One Take Willy", 1977; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975012)
      Ain't Goin' to Wrong You
      Thanks to You
      Song and Dance Man
      Lost at Sea
      Pecos' Blues
      Chronicle: Prince Medoc and The Welsh Indians (excerpts)
    - "Heart on Fire", Dominic Williams, 1987; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975020)
      A list of contents is included with this audiocassette. Side one: home recordings. Side two: songs performed by "New Bracken Band".
      Side 1 / Side 2
      1. Masters and Slaves
      2. Rainbow Over Scotland
      3. All of My Friends
      4. Heart on Fire
      1. Tommy's Lot
      2. Man of the Mountains
      3. Darts to the Heart
    - Bill Sherman, "Reading at Pen and Pencil", Philadelphia, PA, 1985 September 13; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975038)
    - "Allen Fisher from Place, Book I", "The Pogues", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975046)
    - "For Bill", 1984 June 9; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975053)
      A written note on the back of a photograph came with this audiocassette. It is dated July 25, 1984, London and reads: Dear Bill, Just up north for a week hope your well although sometimes I wonder if that's not a silly question. I have been meaning to put this in the post for ages. Thanks for letter with the cheque that I will send it back or use it for a bookletbut cash it I will not. This tape needs updating but will work on a new one all a rush at the moment. Sue is well. Love, Ulli and Sue
    - "New Bracken Band", 1981 March 8; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975061)
    - "Grilikhes / Sherman"; "Waldrop / Grilikhes", undated; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975079)
    - "Jerry Rothenberg", 1988 October 27; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002109975087)
  - Other Materials
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1983-2004, undated; 9 (Box 10)
    - Material removed from printed items, 1996-2003, undated (Box 10)
    - "Maximus To Himself", 1995, undated (Box 10)
    - "Miscellaneous", 1964-2007; 5 (Box 11)
    - Pessoa Blog, 2006, undated (Box 11)
    - Photographs, undated; 3 (Box 11)
    - Printed material, 1966-2004, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    - Printed material, 1966-2004, undated; 4 (Box 12)
    - Olney High School, Philadelphia, yearbook, 1958 (Box 12)
    - Temple University, Philadelphia, yearbook, 1962 (Box 12)
  - Computer media
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - to: 1 Nov. '06, 2007-ycal-12639-0001; 1 (Box 13)
    - to: 03/06, 2007-ycal-12639-0002; 1 (Box 13)
    - to: LABOR DAY, '05 + /to return from Moorea (11/05), 2007-ycal-12639-0003; 1 (Box 13)
    - ends: May 2005, 2007-ycal-12639-0004; 1 (Box 13)
    - LOVING CARESSA (tale, 2001 CE), 2007-ycal-12639-0005; 1 (Box 13)
    - ARCHIVE, 2007-ycal-12639-0006; 1 (Box 13)
    - 1st disc Before Death of Diana, 2007-ycal-12639-0007; 1 (Box 13)
    - Disc #2 (copy: to missed trip) to Moorea, 11/97, 2007-ycal-12639-0008; 1 (Box 13)
    - copy of Disc 3 MINI-ARCHIVE original w/D. HOLMES + daughter Sarah, 2007-ycal-12639-0009; 1 (Box 13)
    - Disc 4 to: 14th trip Moorea, 2007-ycal-12639-0010; 1 (Box 13)
    - The Fifth Disc, 2007-ycal-12639-0011; 1 (Box 13)
    - Disc 6 (to 1999), 2007-ycal-12639-0012; 1 (Box 13)
    - 7, 2007-ycal-12639-0013; 1 (Box 13)
    - [no label information], 2007-ycal-12639-0014; 1 (Box 13)